<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: flatiron school | Traversing the Internets]]></title>
  <link href="http://samueldowens.github.io/blog/categories/flatiron-school/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://samueldowens.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-11T09:50:28-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://samueldowens.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Samuel Owens]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flatiron School Day Eighteen - Suck It Up, Break Your Code.]]></title>
    <link href="http://samueldowens.github.io/blog/2013/10/11/flatiron-school-day-eightteen-refactor_fu/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-11T08:32:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://samueldowens.github.io/blog/2013/10/11/flatiron-school-day-eightteen-refactor_fu</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was going to write another small technical post today but that is going to have to wait until tomorrow. Today I wanted to remind myself and anybody who reads this about the mental blocks with regard to refactoring your code. Here at Flatiron we follow the (I think Kent Beck) motto of &ldquo;Make it work, make it right, make it fast.&rdquo; Sometimes this leads to the first working piece of code being pretty ugly. If you&rsquo;ve just spent hours in a team working through pitfalls to get the code working, it may be overwhelming to go ahead and start refactoring the code once its running and/or all your tests are green.</p>

<p>The big thing I wanted to focus on is that provided you&rsquo;re not living in an alternate dimension where there is no Git, you can feel free to burn your working code to the ground and swim in its ashes. You still have that working code in version control, there is nothing intimidating about altering it to where it starts failing tests or stops functioning. Even if you never find a better solution on a given project, you never will if you don&rsquo;t start smashing your code and trying to rebuild them.</p>

<p>In Office Space they took the printer out into a field after one too many &ldquo;pc load letter&rdquo; errors and smashed it to pieces. Unfortunately with hardware, its pretty difficult to put back together. Count yourself lucky that with code that is not the case, you can destroy your project over and over again and roll it back if you aren&rsquo;t making useful progress.</p>

<p>Get over the fear of the red results and break your code, it&rsquo;s liberating.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flatiron School Day 17 - Class Methods]]></title>
    <link href="http://samueldowens.github.io/blog/2013/10/10/flatiron-school-day-seventeen-class-methods/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-10T08:33:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://samueldowens.github.io/blog/2013/10/10/flatiron-school-day-seventeen-class-methods</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I wanted to write down a little bit about my understanding of how methods work inside of classes and how to know if you want your method to be &lsquo;self.method&rsquo; or just &lsquo;method.&rsquo;</p>

<p>Take the following situation&hellip;</p>

<p>```ruby The Dog Class
class Dog</p>

<p>  attr_accessor :name, :color, :breed, :number_of_legs</p>

<p>end</p>

<p>fido = Dog.new
fido.name = &ldquo;Fido&rdquo;
fido.color = &ldquo;Red&rdquo;
fido.breed = &ldquo;Direwolf&rdquo;
fido.number_of_legs = 4</p>

<p>other_fido = Dog.new
other_fido.name = &ldquo;Not Fido&rdquo;
other_fido.color = &ldquo;Green&rdquo;
other_fido.breed = &ldquo;Regular Wolf&rdquo;
other_fido.number_of_legs = 3
```</p>

<p>So we have the class Dog with a few attributes, and we&rsquo;ve created two dogs. Now we&rsquo;re going to create two methods, one to make an individual dog bark and one to make the Dog class bark.</p>

<p>```ruby I Should Have Named One of the Dogs Charles BARKley.</p>

<p>class Dog</p>

<p>  def barkley</p>

<pre><code>puts "I AM TOTALLY BARKING YOU GUYS"
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def self.bark</p>

<pre><code>puts "THE CONCEPT OF A DOG IS BARKING, RUN FOR YOUR LIVES!"
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>end
```</p>

<p>Now, if we put fido.barkley we will see
&ldquo;I AM TOTALLY BARKING YOU GUYS&rdquo;</p>

<p>If you put fido.bark though, you will get a NoMethodError, because the bark method is defined for the class it was in because we defined it as self.bark, with self referring to the current object its contained within.</p>

<p>So&hellip; If we put Dog.bark we will see
&ldquo;THE CONCEPT OF A DOG IS BARKING, RUN FOR YOUR LIVES!&rdquo;</p>

<p>Similarly, if we were to call Dog.barkley we would again get a NoMethodError because the method is defined without the self demarcation, telling ruby that it is to be used by individual dogs, not by the class as a whole.</p>

<p>So bringing things back around, if you want your overall class to respond to a method, name it as self.method, if you want a specific instance of that class to respond to it, do not have the self in there.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flatiron School Day 16 - The Pareto Principal]]></title>
    <link href="http://samueldowens.github.io/blog/2013/10/09/the-pareto-principal/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-09T08:36:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://samueldowens.github.io/blog/2013/10/09/the-pareto-principal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Pareto principal is also known as the &lsquo;80/20&rsquo; rule. It&rsquo;s a rule I&rsquo;ve heard and seen in various academic endeavours and in business as well. Yesterday was the first time I really looked at it with regard to coding. Avi mentioned during the day that 80% of the work on a project comes in the last 20% of the project and that got me thinking about my work and if the principal applies.</p>

<p>It turns out after looking at my &lsquo;to do&rsquo; list for Flatiron that the only things I have unfinished stand about 80% done. Some are a little further along, some less; but the overwhelming majority of my unfinished work falls right around &lsquo;almost done.&rsquo; It always seems to be that one method I can&rsquo;t get to function correctly, or the one or two tests I just can&rsquo;t seem to get to pass that are holding up some of my work from being completed.</p>

<p>So I&rsquo;ve decided I&rsquo;m going to stop caring about pace. I&rsquo;m not going to find it odd or frustrating anymore when I rush through 80% of a project only to find myself stuck in the mud at the end. I&rsquo;m just going to push through it, knowing that it&rsquo;s completely normal and not something that&rsquo;s going to change.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flatiron School Day Fifteen - Structs]]></title>
    <link href="http://samueldowens.github.io/blog/2013/10/08/flatiron-school-day-fifteen-structs/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-08T08:31:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://samueldowens.github.io/blog/2013/10/08/flatiron-school-day-fifteen-structs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I&rsquo;m going to take a break from &lsquo;talking about my day&rsquo; and instead try and explain something technical. Today I&rsquo;m going to talk about structs, a concept in Ruby we haven&rsquo;t actually learned at Flatiron yet. This article is inspired by the presentation on <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/metaskills/ruby-struct/" title="Speaker Deck by Ken Collins">Speaker Deck by Ken Collins</a>, so thanks Ken for getting me thinking about structs!</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m going to try and break down structs into three parts. Concept, Code and Uses&hellip;</p>

<p><b>Concept:</b> A struct is a miniture class, created quickly and at its core it is a class that only has basic getter and setter methods.</p>

<p><b>Code:</b> There are a few ways to create a struct. I think the easiest to do and understand is as follows&hellip;</p>

<p>```ruby Struct Creation
Location = Struct.new(:name, :lattitude, :longitude)</p>

<p>```
That&rsquo;s all there is to it, this quickly creates a Struct Class called Location that keeps track of a locations name, lattitude and longitude coordinates. Which brings us to&hellip;</p>

<p><b>Uses:</b> Structs seem like they are best used for set values for things that don&rsquo;t need to have any class methods. Things like GPS locations seem like a great reason to use a struct instead of another structure. Any time where you know there is a fixed amount of information you need a struct can be a quick and easy way of storing information about those things, I&rsquo;m going to try and use structs more and see if I can&rsquo;t find even more useful ways to implement them!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flatiron School Day Weekend Two]]></title>
    <link href="http://samueldowens.github.io/blog/2013/10/07/flatiron-school-weekend-two/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-07T08:38:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://samueldowens.github.io/blog/2013/10/07/flatiron-school-weekend-two</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Weekend two was a lot of fun. I managed to end up pretty comfortable with SQL pretty early in the day and we moved onto some other new and interesting things later.</p>

<p>Namely Nokogiri, this ruby gem for scraping web pages was the big learning focus of my weekend. Our project was to use Nokogiri to scrape the Flatiron student webpage for information on each student and export that data into an SQL database. It took a lot of trial and error playing around with Nokogiri before we figured things out, but by the end my whole group was pretty comfortable navigating the trees of data that is HTML.</p>

<p>We also had to redo the quiz from week one but make it object oriented, having to have classes in each of the previous tests. I thought the difficulty on that assignment was pretty easy but that it was useful in providing repetition in looking at grouping things as a class.</p>

<p>Lastly we were given an assignment called playlister, which was a multi-file, multi-class assignment that had a suite of rspec tests that needed to be passed. I sure hope this was the stretch assignment for the weekend as I spent a lot of time struggling with it.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m really looking forward to week three. After two weeks I&rsquo;m already amazed at the tools we&rsquo;re beginning to scratch the surface of using. I can&rsquo;t imagine after 10 more weeks how many cool things we&rsquo;ll be able to build. I feel like a child who just learned what a car can do but whose feet can&rsquo;t yet reach the pedals. Once they can it&rsquo;s going to be a fun time!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
